Gut tov גוט טוב Gut tov today's daf
דף daf is 34. 30 to 4th of July. And we pick
up with
where are we? Oh yes, we are a bit behind. So we're
in the top of Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet ל"ג עמוד ב' Lamed
Gimmel Amud Bet and we're dealing with the debate of Rabbi Akiva
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael where
according to Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva if your tam תם
tam gores then the nizak ניזק, nizak, the one who was damaged,
immediately becomes part owner in it whereas according to Rabbi Ishmael רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael no, you just he's just owed money but he
can collect from the ox. The amount of the debt is limited
to the value of the ox and he can collect from the
ox. The Gemara גמרא Gemara calls it like an apotiki אפותיקי. apotiki.
So he has a very strong lien on the ox, but fundamentally
he's just owed money. Okay, so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara picks
up on the top of Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet ל"ג עמוד ב'.
Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet.
Tani Rav Tachlifa bar Marava תני רב תחליפא בר מערבא. Tani Rav
Tachlifa bar Marava. Line starts with bar Marava בר מערבא bar Marava
about 10 lines down. Kamei d'Rabbi Abahu קמי דרבי אבהו. Kamei d'Rabbi
Abahu. Rav Tachlifa bar Marava רב תחליפא בר מערבא Rav Tachlifa bar
Marava taught in front of Rabbi Abahu רבי אבהו: Rabbi Abahu: Machro
ein machur, hekdesho mukdash מכרו אינו מכור הקדשו מוקדש. Machro ein machur,
hekdesho mukdash. If he sell it, it's not sold, the ox. But
if he sanctify it, it's sanctified. So the first question is who
are we talking about? The mazik מזיק mazik or the nizak ניזק?
nizak? And then also why the inconsistency? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara
says: Machro man מכרו מאן? Machro man? Who's selling it? Ileima mazik
אילימא מזיק, Ileima mazik, the mazik מזיק mazik is selling it, the
original owner of the ox. So machro ein machur מכרו אינו מכור,
machro ein machur, so if you can't sell your ox, mani Rabbi
Akiva hi מני רבי עקיבא היא, mani Rabbi Akiva hi, that would
follow Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva de-amar kulo ha-shor דאמר כולה
השור de-amar kulo ha-shor that the ox goes directly over to the
nizak ניזק. nizak. So it's no longer yours, the original owner. Hekdesho
mukdash הקדשו מוקדש, Hekdesho mukdash, but then why would he be able
to sanctify it? Atu le-Rabbi Ishmael אתו לרבי ישמעאל, Atu le-Rabbi Ishmael,
that fits with Rabbi Ishmael's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael position de-amar shum
meshubad be-bes din דאמר שום משועבד בבית דין de-amar shum meshubad be-bes
din that it's just its value is assessed, but basically the guy
just has a lien on it. So if you can't sell it,
why can you sanctify it? Ela nizak אלא ניזק. Ela nizak. Okay,
so now we're talking about the original owners, the mazik מזיק, mazik,
or we're talking about the nizak ניזק. nizak. Machro ein machur מכרו
אינו מכור, Machro ein machur, you can't sell it, mani Rabbi Ishmael
מני רבי ישמעאל. mani Rabbi Ishmael. Okay, that's Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael that says that the nizak ניזק nizak doesn't own the
ox. So then we're going to have the problem in the reverse.
Hekdesho mukdash הקדשו מוקדש, Hekdesho mukdash, so why can he sanctify it?
Atu le-Rabbi Akiva אתו לרבי עקיבא, Atu le-Rabbi Akiva, that's going according
to Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So like either way, how
does it work according to one half or the other? So the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says: Le-olam mazik לעולם מזיק, Le-olam mazik, we're talking
about the mazik מזיק mazik who's selling and sanctifying. Be-dibrei ha-kol ובדברי
הכל be-dibrei ha-kol and it works according to both positions. That's going
to be interesting. How will that work? So machro ein machur מכרו
אינו מכור. machro ein machur. Oh, he's probably, hold
on. I'm guessing he's locked down.
You want to, alright thanks. Okay, so
okay, so machro ein machur מכרו אינו מכור, machro ein machur, why
isn't it sold if the mazik
מזיק mazik is selling it, the original owner? Afilu le-Rabbi Ishmael אפילו
לרבי ישמעאל Afilu le-Rabbi Ishmael even according to Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael de-amar meshubad lei le-nizak דאמר משועבד ליה לניזק de-amar meshubad
lei le-nizak even according to Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that
says that the mazik מזיק mazik still owns his ox. Why isn't
it sold? De-ha meshubad lei le-nizak דהא משועבד ליה לניזק de-ha meshubad
lei le-nizak because the nizak ניזק nizak has a lien on it.
So it doesn't mean it's not sold at all. It means like
we said yesterday, the original owner can sell it, but then the
nizak ניזק, nizak, it won't be a permanent sale because the nizak
ניזק nizak has a lien and the nizak ניזק nizak will go
and collect it. So machro מכרו machro does not mean machur מכור
machur all. It means not machur מכור machur in a way
to take it away from the nizak ניזק nizak because the nizak
ניזק nizak still has a lien on it and can go and
collect it. But hekdesho mukdash הקדשו מוקדש, hekdesho mukdash, okay, but it
would work to be makdish מקדיש makdish it. Now you could have
just stopped there and said that's Rabbi Ishmael רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael,
hekdesho mukdash הקדשו מוקדש. hekdesho mukdash. Okay, we're talking about the original
owner, if he sells it, it's not a full sale, but if
he's makdish מקדיש makdish it, that's the end of the story. But
the Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to say no, that actually works
even according to Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that the original
owner can be makdish מקדיש. makdish. How could the original owner be
makdish מקדיש makdish according to Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva if
the nizak ניזק nizak owns it? Afilu le-Rabbi Akiva אפילו לרבי עקיבא
Afilu le-Rabbi Akiva mishum d'Rabbi Abahu משום דרבי אבהו mishum d'Rabbi Abahu
because of the teaching of Rabbi Abahu רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abahu. De-amar
Rabbi Abahu דאמר רבי אבהו: De-amar Rabbi Abahu: Gezeira shema yomru hekdesh
yotzei belo pidyon גזירה שמא יאמרו הקדש יוצא בלא פדיון. gezeira shema
yomru hekdesh yotzei belo pidyon. Rabbi Abahu רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu says
that basically if you have a lien on somebody's property and they
sanctify it, okay, according to the ikar halacha עיקר הלכה ikar halacha
you might be able to actually just take it out of hekdesh
הקדש hekdesh without you know, you have your lien. Be sanctifying it
to Bedek Habayis בדק הבית Bedek Habayis as opposed to sanctifying it
as a korban קרבן. korban. Sanctifying it to Bedek Habayis בדק הבית
Bedek Habayis does not undermine the creditor's liens on your property. So
now it's owned by the Bais Hamikdash בית המקדש Bais Hamikdash but
maybe that's no different than if the original owner sold it to
a third party where the creditors can now come and take it
away. So Bedek Habayis בדק הבית Bedek Habayis is a kedusha קדושה
kedusha that is rooted in the Bais Hamikdash's בית המקדש Bais Hamikdash
ownership. So when you sanctify it to Bedek Habayis בדק הבית Bedek
Habayis it's like you basically sold it to a third party. The
creditors come, they take it away, they're now the owners of it
and the kedusha קדושה kedusha goes off because they're now just exercising
the lien. So it certainly works if you say, and there's a
whole debate about when somebody exercises
the
lien.
So,
okay, so thank you, thank you. Okay, so where are we? So,
okay, so
even if you sell, even if, so we're basically dealing with the
debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael about
whether the ניזק Nizak has a lien on the ox or owns
the ox. And what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that
if the original מזיק Mazik sells it, then the sale would obviously
not be good according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that the ניזק
Nizak owns it, but even according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that
the ניזק Nizak has a lien, the sale would not be permanent
because the ניזק Nizak can go and exercise his lien and go
ahead and collect it. That's number one. Now, how about if the
original owner sanctifies it? So according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that
obviously would not work because the ניזק Nizak owns it. But even
according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that the הקדש Hekdesh does work,
okay, the ניזק Nizak can go and exercise his lien and take
this out of הקדש. Hekdesh. And, but nevertheless, even though he's allowed
to take it out of הקדש, Hekdesh, he has to give some
type of a small amount to הקדש Hekdesh as a type of
an act of פדיון, Pidyon, of redeeming the הקדש, Hekdesh, so it
should not look like that you can just take something away from
הקדש Hekdesh and make the קדושה Kedusha go off. Here that actually
might work, because if he actually has an original lien, then he's
able to exercise that lien and ultimately that trumps the act of
it having been, as this person having been מקדיש Makdish it. But
nevertheless, since for the interim it was in the possession of הקדש,
Hekdesh, he actually goes ahead and gives some type of a money
to do an act of redemption. So again, this ברייתא Baraita taught
that if the מזיק Mazik sells it, it's no good. Why is
that? According to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because the ניזק Nizak already
owns the ox. According to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, it really is
a good sale, but it's not a permanent sale because the ניזק
Nizak can exercise his liens. If
he's מקדיש Makdish it, it says
it is קדוש. Kadosh. So according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, we
understand, wait did I say that right?
הקדישו, Hikdisho, right, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, if he's הקדישו, Hikdisho, right,
it is קדוש. Kadosh. So according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, because
the original owner actually owns it still, the מזיק Mazik actually owns
it. And according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even though the ניזק
Nizak owns it, okay, nevertheless, because it was, did this act of
הקדש, Hekdesh, and it looks like it belongs to הקדש, Hekdesh, even
now that it really was always the ניזק's Nizak's ox, we would
treat it as if it was קדוש Kadosh and you'd have to
do this type of a פדיון. Pidyon. Okay, so הקדישו מוקדש, Hikdisho
mukdash, basically according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the ניזק Nizak can
exercise his lien and retrieve it, but he has to do an
act of פדיון Pidyon because it genuinely belonged to הקדש Hekdesh in
the interim. And even if his lien trumps, he has to do
an act of פדיון Pidyon so it looks like it just doesn't,
the הקדש Hekdesh doesn't go away automatically. And certainly according to רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he real, you know,
where it always belonged to the ניזק, Nizak, the הקדש Hekdesh really
didn't work at all, and the ניזק Nizak really is completely entitled
to just take his ox. Nevertheless, he does this act of פדיון
Pidyon so it doesn't look like you're taking something away from הקדש
Hekdesh without an act of פדיון. Pidyon. Yes, Josh, you're a good...
are we going to cover the case where he consecrates it as
a
קרבן?
Korban? Not here. I mean, I don't know if we're going to
have it later, but if you מקדיש Makdish it as a קרבן,
Korban, then it changes it. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Okay, we're
starting at the two dots on ל"ג ל"ב Lamed Gimmel Lamed Bet
for those who just came in. In a way, we're going to
sort of review everything we just said. שור תם שהזיק, Shor Tam
she-hizik,
a tame ox that damaged. עד שלא עמד בדין, Ad she-lo amad
ba-din, before there was the court case. מכר מכור הקדישו מוקדש, Machar
machur hekdesho mukdash, if you sold it, it's a good sale, if
you sanctified it, it's good הקדש. Hekdesh. שחטו ונתנו במתנה, Shachto ונתנו
במתנה u-nesano be-matana, if you slaughtered it and gave it as a
gift, presumably this is all talking about the מזיק. Mazik. The גמרא's
Gemara's going to unpack all of this. מה שעשה עשוי, Mah she-asa
asui, then it's done. Presumably the ניזק Nizak is out his ox.
משיעמד בדין, Mi-she-amad ba-din, however, once there was a court case, so
presumably at that time there was a court case and now it's
been given over to the ניזק. Nizak. So מכר אינו מכור, Machar
eino machur, the sale isn't good. הקדישו אינו מוקדש, Hekdesho eino mukdash,
sanctifying it isn't good. Presumably talking about the מזיק Mazik doing all
of this. קדמו בעלי חובות וגבו, Kidmu baalei chovot ve-higbiu, now let's
say the creditors came, creditors of the מזיק Mazik came to collect
the ox. Okay, בין חב עד שלא הזיק, Bein chav ad she-lo
hizik, whether the damage occurred, whether the מזיק Mazik borrowed the money
before the ox did damage, so the creditors had a lien on
him before the ניזק Nizak had a lien on him. בין הזיק
עד שלא חב, Bein hizik ad she-lo chav, whether the נזק Nezek
happened first, so whoever has the prior, regardless of who has the...
prior lien, לא עשו ולא כלום, lo asu velo klum, if the
creditors took the ox, it doesn't work, לפי שאין משתלם אלא מגופו,
lefi she'ein mishtalem ela miguffo, because the ניזק nizak can only collect
from the body of it. Okay, so that was a very, very
packed משנה, mishnah, the גמרא gemara's going to unpack all of that.
Okay, now,
מועד, muad, however, if an animal is not a תם tam but
habitual, שהזיק shehizik and damaged, בין עמד בדין בין שלא עמד בדין,
bein amad bedin bein shelo amad bedin, whether before or after the
court case, right, you don't pay from the body of the animal,
you just owe money. So in that case the ניזק nizak has
no rights to the animal
itself, so מכר מכור, makhar makhur, הקדישו מוקדש, hikdisho mukdash, the original
owner can sell it, can sanctify it, שחטו ונתנו במתנה מה שעשה
עשוי, shakhato unetano bematanah mah she'asah asui, he can give it away,
he can שחט shekht it, okay, קדמו בעלי חובות והגביהו, kadmu ba'alei
chovot vehigbihu, or if the creditors came and they collected the ox,
בין חב עד שלא הזיק בין הזיק עד שלא חב, bein chav
ad shelo hizik bein hizik ad shelo chav, regardless of whether the
debt came first or whether the damage came first, מה שעשה עשוי,
mah she'asah asui, they can keep the ox that they took, לפי
שאין משתלם אלא מן העלייה, lefi she'ein mishtalem ela min ha'aliyah, because
you only pay from cash, you don't pay from the body of
the ox. So in the case where it's a מועד, muad, obviously
the original owner can do what he wants with the ox, the
ניזק nizak has no rights to the ox and so on. The
issue is when it's a תם tam and there a lot of
the difference of when does the control transfer matters in the case
of עמד בדין. amad bedin. Now I want to just pause a
moment and make a point that תוספות tosafot makes, but that gets
debated a lot in the אחרונים, acharonim, in the ראשונים, rishonim, which
is, even according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says, and it's
clear from our גמרא gemara that the גמרא gemara understands that according
to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of חלוט הוא השור, chalut hu hashor,
that the ניזק nizak becomes an automatic owner, that that happens automatically.
That is a little bit ironic, because the normal הלכה halacha by
קנס, knas, right, if we פוסקין pasken that חצי נזק קנסא, chatzi
nezek knasa, which is what we פוסקין, pasken, normally קנס knas does
not become a reality until you're העמדה בדין. ha'amadah bedin. Meaning, if
I borrow money from you, or I break your car or whatever
it is, there's a reality that I owe you money whether or
not you've taken me to court yet. Okay, the very fact that
I borrowed money or that I did a damage creates this idea
of reality, the court clarifies the fact that I owed you money,
enforces it, but that's a reality that exists without the court, whether
the court does it or not.
Now, however, if I actually did something that I now owe you
a קנס, knas, let's say I don't know, my ox gored your
slave and now I have to pay you thirty כסף. kesef. Until
there's an העמדה בדין, ha'amadah bedin, I don't owe you a penny.
Okay, because it's not like an objective reality, or let's take a
better example where it's clear that it's you see it as a
fine and as a punishment. I do a גניבה gneivah from you,
I burgle some property from you. So there's an objective reality before
the court case, which is before there is a court case, which
is that I owe you the principal. But the double payment, that's
only a fine imposed by the court. Before there is that court
case, I don't owe you that money. Okay, the court doesn't just
clarify and identify it, it creates the debt, it imposes the debt.
So therefore, even once we פוסקין חצי נזק הוא קנס, pasken chatzi
nezek hu knas,
even according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you might say with before
a court case, how could you become an immediate part owner in
my ox? The court has to impose that debt. And nevertheless, the
גמרא gemara understands and תוספות tosafot asks why this is true, but
the גמרא gemara understands that no, according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
it happens automatically. Maybe because they learn it from the פסוק, pasuk,
right, ומכרו את השור החי, umakhru et hashor hachai, it sounds like
that's an automatic reality. So even though it's a קנס, knas, you
become a part owner automatically. So this ברייתא braita that we just
taught that we're now about to unpack, that speaks about a shift
between העמדה בדין ha'amadah bedin before and after there's a court case,
after there's a court case you get more rights to my ox,
beforehand you don't. You could have said that's even true according to
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because that's a reality about קנס, knas, but
that's not the way the גמרא gemara's going to focus. The גמרא
gemara's going to assume that according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even
without the court case, you own it automatically. So let's take a
look at what the גמרא gemara does with this. Okay, אמר מר,
amar mar, let's go back and unpack what we just saw.
מכר מכור, makhar makhur, מכר מכור, makhar makhur, so if you sell
it it's still sold, okay, this is before there's a court case.
So we're going to read this according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael,
because it's clear that it's working within רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that
sees that the original owner first has a lot of rights in
his cow before, in his ox before the court case. It's a
תם. tam. Okay, so if the original owner sold it, the מזיק,
mazik, it works. לרדייא, leradya, that means that the person who bought
it can use it for plowing until the ניזק nizak exercises his
lien. The ניזק nizak can eventually exercise his lien, so it's not
totally out of the control of the ניזק, nizak, but it's out
of the control of the ניזק nizak until and the purchaser has
a right to use it until the ניזק nizak exercises his lien.
הקדישו מוקדש, hikdisho mukdash, if he sanctifies it it works, משום דרבי
אבהו. mishum deRabbi Abbahu. Now that also doesn't mean permanent, okay, that
means that because ultimately the ניזק nizak can exercise his lien, the
same way he can take it out of the hands of a
third party, he can take it out of the hands of הקדש,
hekdesh, so he really doesn't even have to do any act of
פדיון, pidyon, he can exercise his lien and get it away. from
הקדש. hekdesh. But nevertheless, because of רבי אבהו, Rabbi Avu, he has
to give הקדש hekdesh some nominal amount so it doesn't look like
something is losing its קדושה, kedusha, you know, automatically, like, you know,
without a proper process. Okay, שחטו ונתנו במתנה מה שעשה עשוי, shachto
unetano b'matana mah she'asa asui, right?
If he slaughtered it and gave it away, it's done. Again, the
simple read of this ברייתא, braita, the גמרא Gemara is significantly limiting,
right, the simple read of this ברייתא. braita. The simple read of
this ברייתא braita is according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, you really
can completely get the ox away from the ניזק, nizak, right? If
you gave it away to a different party, you did something to
it, the ניזק nizak is out. That's the simple read of the
ברייתא. braita. The גמרא Gemara is pulling back and saying, no, even
according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the ניזק nizak has a strong
lien, and he can retrieve it from parties that it was sold
to. So what does it mean, what's שחטו ונתנו במתנה, shachto unetano
b'matana, it's done? So let's say, or given away. בשלמא נתנו במתנה,
bishlama netano b'matana, when you say it was given as a gift,
מה שעשה עשוי, mah she'asa asui, it was done, doesn't mean done
permanently. It means done לרדיא, l'radya, that the third party can now
use it to plow until the ניזק nizak exercises his lien. אלא
שחטו, ela shachto, but what do you mean if it's slaughtered, it's
the end of the story, the ניזק nizak is out? ליתי ולישקול
מבשריה, leisay v'lishkol mibisrei,
let the ניזק nizak collect from the meat? So, okay, even if
the animal isn't alive, he still can collect from the meat of
it. דתניא, d'tanya, חי, chai, it says, אין לי אלא חי, ein
li ela chai, it says, right, it says ומכרו את השור החי,
umachru es hashor hachai, sell the living ox. Maybe only if the
ox is still living. שחטו מנין, shachto minayin, how do you know
if he slaughtered it, the ניזק nizak still has rights to the
ox? תלמוד לומר ומכרו את השור, talmud lomar umachru es hashor, מכל
מקום, mikol makom, you just stop before you get to the word
חי. chai. So anyway, what does it mean that it's slaughtered, it's
over? אמר רב שיזבי, Amar Rav Shizbi, לא נצרכה אלא לפחת שחיטה.
lo nitzrecha ela l'pachas shechita. It doesn't mean that the ניזק nizak
can no longer collect from the animal once it's slaughtered. It means
that if after the slaughtering, now the value has gone down, and
it does not pay the entire damage, then the ניזק nizak is
out. Okay, so this, I, my ox gored yours, I owe you
a hundred dollars, the ox was worth a hundred dollars, you would
have become, you had a lien on the entire value of my
ox. I slaughtered it, now it's only worth eighty dollars. Okay, sorry,
you can collect eighty dollars, but you can't collect the full hundred.
Now, by the way, remember, according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, actually
I owe you a hundred dollars. So if you actually can seize
other property of mine, or get me to court and get me
to pay in cash, you'll get your full hundred dollars. But if
let's say there's no other property of mine to claim other than
this, so the actual circumstances in which you lose money are limited
because according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael I do owe you the
money. It's not that you just have the ox, you have a
lien on the ox. But if that was the only thing you
could have collected from, now you're out. I'm sorry, then you only
have eighty dollars to collect from. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay,
אמר רב אבויה בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Avuiah brei d'Rav Yehoshua,
זאת אומרת, zos omeres, this teaches you, המזיק שעבודו של חבירו פטור,
hamazik shibudo shel chaveiro patur, that if somebody damages his friend's lien
that somebody else has, you're exempt. Meaning, I owe you a hundred
dollars. You have a lien on my plot of land. Okay, you
know what I'm going to do? I'm going to go plow that
plot of land over with salt. I'm going to go ahead and
destroy that plot of land. It's still mine, it's not yours yet,
okay? You just have a lien on it. Now you're coming to
collect. I don't have any cash. All you can do is collect
from that plot of land, but because of what I just did
to it, you're not going to get your full money back. Now
it's only worth fifty dollars, not a hundred dollars. Okay, so do
I have to pay you? I indirectly caused you loss. But when
I damaged it, it was my plot of land. So I was
מזיק שעבודו של חבירו. mazik shibudo shel chaveiro. I damaged my thing
that you had a lien on. Okay, do I now have to
reimburse you for that? Okay, now the funny thing is, which I
don't really get, is that I don't understand, if I have the
money to reimburse you, then why don't you just collect that money
in my debt or something? So I'm not exactly getting that because
I still owe you the money, right? So but it's here just
a question about what you're collecting from. But anyway, that act of
destroying it does not make me incur a direct debt to you.
It was only caused an indirect loss to you. So the same
thing here, I slaughtered the cow. Why don't I have to pay
you for damaging property that you had a lien on? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא, pishita, obviously, that's exactly what we're saying.
No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought,
התם הוא דאמר ליה לא חסרתיך ולא מידי, hasam hu d'amar lei
lo chasartich v'lo midi, דאמר ליה זיקא בעלמא הוא דשקלי מינך. d'amar
lei zika b'alma hu d'shakli minach. Maybe I would say, no, the
reason you don't pay when you slaughter the cow is you could
say, I didn't really damage a thing you had a lien on.
I didn't really damage the cow, I just took away some winds
from it, you know? It's still the same cow, it's just dead.
It just doesn't have the spirit of life in it, but I
didn't really damage it. אבל בעלמא, aval b'alma, but if I plow,
destroyed a plot of land, לחייב, lichayiv, then maybe I would have
to, then I really destroyed it. קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, very funny,
why he would think that slaughtering something and turning it from living
to dead and worthless is not destroying it in, you know, damaging
it the same way other things. Anyway fine. So you need to
tell me that even if you really damage a plot of land,
you're also exempt. קא משמע דהא נמי רבא אמרה. Ka mashma de-ha
nami Rava amrah. I could have learned it out from what Rava
said. דאמר רבא: De'amar Rava: השורף שטרו של חבירו פטור. Ha-soref shtaro
shel chaveiro patur. If I burn your debt document I'm exempt. Okay,
so you have a document that says that I owe you a
hundred dollars. All right, I go ahead and I'm going to burn
the document. Fine, I'll pay you the dollar for the piece of
paper. Okay, but the reality is what I've done is I've now
made it a lot harder for you to collect your debt because
you can't prove it right now. Okay, but I didn't actually destroy
the property that you own, like the hundred dollars. I didn't destroy
the hundred dollars, I just destroyed the evidence of the hundred dollars.
Okay, now this is going to be a גמרא Gemara later on
in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, we're going to get to this discussion.
It's called דיני דגרמי. Dinei de-garmi. When you do an act that
you cause indirect damage but it is such a clear
either it's much more on the side of direct than indirect or
the consequence of that act is much more sort of clear and
immediate that there's going to be times when we don't just treat
it as גרמא, grama, we treat it as a high degree of
fault or causation and you're actually going to pay and that's called
דיני דגרמי. Dinei de-garmi. But anyway here we are saying that you're
going to be פטור. patur. Now that's not exactly the same as
שיעבודו של חבירו. shibudo shel chaveiro. In one case I damaged the
property that you have a lien on, in the other case and
actually your lien might be seen as a quasi-ownership and maybe we
would treat it as I actually damaged some type of property that
you have a partial ownership to. Here I didn't damage the actual
debt itself or the lien itself, I only damaged the evidence that
you had. You're still owed the money, you still have the reality
of the lien, you're just now going to have a harder time
of proving it in a court case, in a בית דין. Beit
Din. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: no, so I can't infer
from the case of burning the שטר. shtar. מהו דתימא, Ma'u deteyma,
I might have said: התם הוא דאמר ליה ניירא בעלמא קא קלימנא
מינך, Hatam hu de'amar leh neyara be'alma ka kalimna minach, I just
burned a piece of paper, okay, you know, the money's still owed
you, you still have the lien, you just can't prove it anymore.
אבל היכא דחפר בה בורות שיחין ומערות, Aval heyka dechafar bah borot
shichin u-me'arot, but if you actually dig ditches in a person's plot
of land that a person had a lien on, לחייב, lechayev, maybe
you would be חייב. chayav. קא משמע לן דהא הכא כמאן דחפר
בה בורות שיחין ומערות דמי. Ka mashma lan deha hacha keman dechafar
bah borot shichin u-me'arot dami. So that's why we're saying no, in
that case you're also פטור patur because שחטינג shechting the cow is
like digging ditches in the plot of land. אגופא מה שעשה עשוי
Agufa mah she'asah asuy and it says it's done because even though
this person now he has less to collect from, you when you
destroyed it, it was your object, so therefore you technically are exempt
from payment. All right, now again the funny thing is that you
still owe him the full hundred dollars, so even though the dead
animal is only worth eighty, if you have the twenty dollars to
pay him in addition he can still collect it from you in
other ways. But anyway you don't have a direct liability for מזיק
mazik for damaging it because it is your object that you שחט-ed.
shecht So again what this ברייתא braita says is: לפני העמדה בדין,
Lifnei ha'amadah badin, you go ahead and you can do what you
want, sell it, sanctify it, it is done. The simple read of
that ברייתא braita is according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the guy's
lien is meaningless to prevent you, you know, he can't use it
at all. It's like you sold it, it's out of his control.
The גמרא Gemara re-reads it to say that that guy actually has
a strong lien and in most cases he can retrieve it. You
sold it, he gets it back, you הקדיש-ed hektash it, he gets
it back. So the גמרא Gemara is strengthening the idea of the
lien of the ניזק nizak against the simple sense of the ברייתא.
braita. The simple sense of the ברייתא braita is according to רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, לפני העמדה בדין, Lifnei ha'amadah badin, you can totally
remove it from the control of the ניזק. nizak. Okay, but לאחר
העמדה בדין, le-achar ha'amadah badin, presumably what happened in העמדה בדין ha'amadah
badin is that the court actually awarded it to that person, allowed
you to that was when you exercised your control and then it
fully belonged your exercised your lien and then that's when it fully
belongs to the ניזק. nizak. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, קדמו בעלי חובות וגבו. Kadmu ba'alei chovot vegavu. Now let's say
the creditors came and they exercised their liens on they exercised you
know their lien you know they went and they collected their debt
here. בין חב עד שלא הזיק בין הזיק עד שלא חב לא
עשו ולא כלום. Bein chav ad shelo hizik bein hizik ad shelo
chav lo asu velo chelum. So whether they whether you owed the
מזיק mazik owed money before the damage or after the damage, if
they go ahead and they exercise their liens, the בעלי חובות, ba'alei
chovot, it's too bad, לפי שאין משלם אלא מגופו Lefi she'ein meshalem
ela migufo because you only because you can only get you the
ניזק nizak can only get paid up from the body of the
animal itself. So what does this mean?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, hold on I just want
to see one thing.
Okay, so this is לאחר העמדה בדין. le-achar ha'amadah badin. After העמדה
בדין ha'amadah badin their collection is no good. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: בשלמא הזיק עד שלא חב, Bishlama hizik ad shelo
chav, I understand that if the damage occurred before the מזיק mazik
took out a loan, נזיקין קדמו, nezikin kadmu, so that's why the
damage the people that you know the ניזק nizak has a prior
lien and that's why he can go ahead and take it away
from the creditor because his lien came sooner.
אבל חב Aval chav If the loan occurred before the damage, so
בעל חוב קודם, Ba'al Chov Kodem, so then the money first was
owed to the creditor before, thank you, well I just need to
drink some, thank you. Okay, before it was owed to the ניזק.
Nizak. Okay, so if that's true, if first basically I owe money
to a creditor and then my ox goes and gores and then
I owe money to the ניזק Nizak and my creditor comes and
he takes my ox, why should the ניזק Nizak have a right
to take it away from him? Okay, I mean, the creditor had
an earlier lien, בעל חוב קודם. Ba'al Chov Kodem. ואפילו הזיק עד
שלא חב Ve'afilu Hizik Ad Shelo Chav and anyway the גמרא Gemara
says, even in the case where first it damaged before I borrowed
the money, בעל חוב קודם. Ba'al Chov Kodem. So even in that
case, if we would say that the,
that, wait
a minute, hold on, let me,
right, if we would say ואפילו הזיק עד שלא חב בעל חוב
קודם, Ve'afilu Hizik Ad Shelo Chav Ba'al Chov Kodem, so, ah,
one minute, wait, hold on, hold on, I'm sorry.
ואפילו הזיק עד
שלא חב. Ve'afilu
Hizik Ad Shelo
Chav.
Oh right, alright, okay, right, ואפילו הזיק עד שלא חב, Ve'afilu Hizik
Ad Shelo Chav, I got, ואפילו הזיק עד שלא חב, Ve'afilu Hizik
Ad Shelo Chav, even if the damage occurred before the debt, בעל
חוב קודם, Ba'al Chov Kodem, if the בעל חוב Ba'al Chov came
and actually seized it prior, so maybe he should be entitled to
it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is saying like this, if I
owed the money to the creditors before, the ברייתא Braita again teaches
that if the creditors took the cow, okay, it doesn't matter whether
I owed them money first or I owed the ניזק Nizak first,
it doesn't matter, the ניזק Nizak can take the cow away from
them. That's what the ברייתא Braita teaches. Okay, even after the creditors
took it, the ניזק Nizak can take the cow away from them.
So the גמרא Gemara says, I don't understand. Okay, if the, if
I first owed money to the ניזק, Nizak, then, I'm sorry, if
I first owed money to the creditors, then why should the ניזק
Nizak be able to take it away from them? The creditors had
an earlier lien. Even if I first owed money to the ניזק,
Nizak, the creditors still were the first one to seize the property.
And here's an interesting question: If I owe different people money and
one, and somebody who I owed money later to took the money,
was the first to seize the property, is it clear that the
person I owed money earlier to can take it away from him
or not? That's not so clear. So the גמרא Gemara is saying
this doesn't make any sense. If I owed the creditors money first,
they certainly should be able to get the property
away from the, they certainly should be able to keep the property
if they took it, if I owed the creditors first. But even
if I owed the creditors last, it's possible that they should be
able to keep the property. ואפילו הזיק עד שלא חב, Ve'afilu Hizik
Ad Shelo Chav, even if I owed the creditors last, בעל חוב
קודם, Ba'al Chov Kodem, since the creditors took the property first, maybe
they should be able to keep it. שמע מינה, Shema Mina, should
I learn from this, בעל חוב מאוחר שקדם וגבה מה שגבה לא
גבה, Ba'al Chov Me'uchar Shekodem Vegava Ma Shegava Lo Gava, that if
a later creditor took the property, he's not able to keep it?
An earlier creditor could take it away from him. Okay, so if
I owed the creditors the money first, they certainly should be allowed
to keep it. Even if I owed them the money last, it's
possible they should be allowed to keep it because we have a
debate if a later creditor takes property, if he's allowed to keep
it or not. Okay, so how does this make it any sense?
So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם אימא לך מה שגבה גבה. Le'olam
Eima Lach Ma Shegava Gava. No, I could tell you, normally if
a later creditor takes it, he's allowed to keep it. And if
this was a normal הלכה, Halacha, the creditors would certainly be allowed
to keep it. If they were an earlier, if I owed them
money first, of course they'd be allowed to keep what they took,
they were the first creditors. And if I owed them money last,
maybe they'd be allowed to keep it if they were the first
ones to seize the property. So if that's true, why is it
that the ניזק Nizak can retrieve the property from them here? ושאני
התם דאמר ליה אילו גבך הוה. Veshani Hatam De'amar Lei Illu Gabach
Havei. Here
is why the ניזק Nizak can take it away from the creditors
if the creditors took the cow, because they can say to the
creditors, אילו גבך הוה לאו מינך הוה גבינא ליה, Illu Gabach Havei
Lav Minach Havah Gavina Lei, let's say you had that cow originally,
the ox, let's say I didn't have the, so so Hillel goes
ahead and he seized this ox because I owed Hillel a hundred
dollars. I'm sorry, I said Hillel, I meant there's Hillel, thank you.
Okay, so I owe Hillel, I owe Hillel a hundred dollars, he
went ahead and he took the ox in payment of what I
owe him. Tovi goes here and he says it's too bad, you
know, Dov's ox damaged mine, I'm taking it away from you Hillel.
Why are you entitled to do that if normally you can't take
it away from a creditor who seized the property? Because you can
say to Hillel, let's say you had that ox all along, I
would still have a right to collect from it towards my ox,
so I'm going ahead and. I'm going to go ahead and collect
it right now. אילו גבך הוה לאו מינך הוה גבינא ליה? Ilu
gabak hava lo minach havina gavayle? Look, even if that ox had
always been by you, wouldn't I have had a right to collect
it for my ox? It gored my ox. דהאי תורא דאזקן מיניה
משתלמנא. dehai tora deazkin minei mishtalamna. I'm going to go ahead and
because because the ox that damaged me, that's the ox I'm going
to collect from. Now that makes no sense because if the ox
was by Hillel, then the only reason Charlie would have a right
to collect from him is if Hillel was negligent in watching it.
But he wasn't the one who was negligent in watching it. I
was the one negligent in watching it. So I was negligent in
watching, I owe Charlie money, and Hillel goes ahead and he takes
my ox in payment. What allows Charlie to take the ox away
from Hillel? Hillel might have been an earlier creditor or even if
he was a later creditor, he was the first one to seize
it. So תוספות Tosafot says this is really just a fancy way
of saying, and if you really want, it's really the line in
the ברייתא Baraita itself. The last line in the
ברייתא Baraita is לפי שאין משלם אלא מגופו. lefi she’ein meshalem ela
migufo. But it really is just a fancy way of saying is,
yes of course Charlie can take away the ox
because Charlie's lien is focused on the ox itself. Hillel can collect
from any of my property. So the reason Charlie is able to
take it away from Hillel is not because he had an earlier
lien, he might have even had a later lien, but he had
a focused lien on the ox. And therefore he has a greater
right to that ox than to any of the other of my
property, and that entitles him to take the ox away from Hillel,
and Hillel can come and collect from me from other property that
I have. Yes.
This is, is this a general distinction between regular liens
from loans and damages in the way that you collect?
No, the גמרא Gemara actually is treating this just like a regular
lien.
That's what I'm thinking.
It's just saying that it's different here because you only have specifically
on the ox, you have a very focused lien, what the גמרא
Gemara called before an אפותיקי apoteiki and that gives you special rights.
Okay,
let's get to the, let's keep on going. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
שור שווה מאתיים
שנגח שור שווה מאתיים וחבל בו בחמישים זוז ושבח ועמד על ארבע
מאות זוז.
shor shaveh matayim shenagach shor shaveh matayim vechabal bo bechamishim zuz
veshavach veamad al arba meot zuz. Okay,
an ox worth 200 damaged another ox worth 200 and it did
50 worth of damage. And now the original ox that was, I'll
draw a little drawing,
I think I was
losing people a little bit there before.
Okay,
here's ראובן's Reuven ox, we'll call it ראובן, Reuven, and here's שמעון's
Shimon ox. Okay? And they're each worth 200.
And he damaged שמעון Shimon and did $50 worth of damage. Okay?
וחבל בו בחמישים זוז. vechabal bo bechamishim zuz.
And then, there it is again,
ושבח ועמד על ארבע מאות זוז. veshavach veamad al arba meot zuz.
Then all of a sudden the market went up or the ox
got stronger or whatever it is, and now it's worth 400. Okay?
It improved in value. שאילו לא הזיקו היה עומד על שמונה מאות
זוז. sheilu lo heziko haya omed al shmoneh meot zuz. But had
it not suffered any damage, it now would be worth 800.
נותן כשעת הנזק. noten kisha'at hanezek. How much do I pay? I
pay the original 50. There was original 50 of damage, I'm going
to pay 25. Okay? You don't say I'm going to have to
pay, oh look, I can tell you, you made, it's now worth,
it would have been worth 800 had you not damaged me, so
you caused me 400 worth of damage, you have to pay me,
no no no. That's just indirect. The amount of damage is assessed
by the moment of the damage. At the moment of the damage
it was 50, so you're going to pay 25. You're not going
to look at the fact of like you caused it eventually to
be worth 400 less than it would have been. Okay. כחש כשעת
העמדה בדין. kachash kisha'at ha'amada badin. Now let's say however
that before we got to court, it went down from 50, I
mean 150, and now it was worth 100. Okay? This was, okay,
we actually have to do a timeline here.
Okay, so this is, this is Monday and this is Tuesday. Okay?
So in, let's say it went down in value. Now it's worth
100. And this is when we have the court case. We have
the court case on Tuesday. So in this case, how much am
I going to pay? So in this case I'm going to pay,
I'm going to pay 50. Okay? Or actually I'm going to pay
25. Okay? Because the damage is 50. And we don't say the
damage based on how much it's the higher value, we say the
damage based on this value. In this case, we're going to say
no, actually in this case it actually caused $100 worth of damage
and therefore I'm going to pay 50. Okay? So it's, it's not
parallel. Okay? This is considered to be an indirect cause of loss
that it didn't go up as much. And this one it actually
gets worth less, okay, goes down in value as opposed to not
going up as much in value, it goes down in value, we're
going to say that's all a result of the original damage. So
I damaged it, it went from being worth 200, eventually it went
down to being worth 100. So I caused $100 worth of damage.
So even though this was a loss, this wasn't an appreciation of
the. Value wasn't worth less than the original amount, it was just
a, it did not become worth as much as it would have
been worth.
Does the 200 also go down? I mean how much it was
worth before it got hurt?
Well, the גמרא's Gemara going to say the reason it went down
is not because the market went down. The reason it went down
is because it kept on depreciating because of the original injury.
Right, if it was just that the market went down, then that
would be very inconsistent. Okay, but this is actually going to be
seen as a depreciation that resulted from the original injury. And even
though this also was a loss, this was a loss of profit.
I don't pay you for loss of profit. But this was a
continued injury that kept getting worse and worse, so there I do
pay you for.
Okay, okay.
שבח מזיק, שבח מזיק נותנים
לו
כשעת הנזק. Shevach mazik, shevach mazik notnim lo kesha'at hanezek. פחת דכשעמד
בדין. Pachat deche'amad bedin. Now let's say
actually the,
one minute, let me just make sure I got this right.
Now let's say I, the מזיק, mazik, go ahead
and
make this animal, wait a minute, hold on, hold on,
let me see,
just one second.
Right, right, right.
Right, so let's say instead of this animal,
the ניזק's nisak cow, Shimon's cow, changing value, let's say this cow
changed value. Okay, so let's say here, okay, after the original amount,
the cow went up to be worth 400. Okay, so why don't
you, why can't Shimon now say, look, you owed me $25, okay,
wait, how much did it say? שש שלוש מאתיים שנה שש שלוש
מאתיים. Shesh shalosh matayim shana shesh shalosh matayim. Okay, you owed me,
you owed me,
you owed me $25. I had a portion of this, I had
whatever, what's $25 of 200? Whatever, 12.5%. Anyway, whatever it would be,
I had a certain percent of this animal, okay, because of the,
because of the $25 worth of, worth of payment that you owed
me. Now it went up, I'm going to get a continued 12.5%
of this animal, okay, right? Which makes sense according to רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. You're right. According to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that would
make sense.
Okay, you get the increase with it. But it says that's not
true. נותנים לו כשעת הנזק. Notnim lo kesha'at hanezek. You don't. You
still, if here you had $25 worth of this animal, you still
have only $25 worth of that animal. That sounds like we're dealing
with a רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. Otherwise you should, your value should
increase. Okay. פחת דכשעמד בדין. Pachat deche'amad bedin. But let's say it
went down to a hundred. Then in that case you're only going
to get $12.50.
You actually do lose out. So that's very inconsistent, right? If you
have a portion of the animal, you should get its increased value.
If you, if you don't have a portion of the animal, you're
just owed a straight $25, then you should still be owed $25
even if the animal goes down. Okay, so this, we have to
explain both of these inbalance. All right, let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר מר, Amar mar, let's unpack this. שבח מזיק נותנים לו כשעת
הנזק. Shevach mazik notnim lo kesha'at hanezek. So the גמרא Gemara does
not feel it needs to unpack this. This makes sense. Well, I
mean we're going to have to understand this. This is going to
be because it's considered the injury continued as a result of the
original one. Okay, but this in general we understand that you don't
pay for an indirect loss of profit. That's this. You don't pay
for an indirect loss of profit. This is seen as though a
result of the original injury, a continued depreciation based on the original
injury. We're going to look at this though, this really doesn't make
sense. Okay. So it says like this, שבח מזיק נותנים לו כשעת
הנזק מני רבי ישמעאל. Shevach mazik notnim lo kesha'at hanezek mani Rabbi
Ishmael. The fact that here even when it goes up, you're still
only paying $25, means you don't have a portion of the animal.
That works like רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, that it's not a portion,
it's just a debt. דאמר בעל חוב וזוזי הוא דמסיק ליה. De'amar
ba'al chov vezozei hu demasik lei.
It's only a debt. Okay. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at the
end. פחת דכשעמד בדין אתן רבי עקיבא דאמר שותפין נינהו. Pachat deche'amad
bedin atan Rabbi Akiva de'amar shutfin ninhu.
But here if it goes down, you get, you get based on
the current value, you know, so now you only get $12.50. That's
a רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that's a percentage of the animal. So
this doesn't make any sense. So the גמרא Gemara says רישא רבי
ישמעאל וסיפא רבי עקיבא? Reisha Rabbi Ishmael veseifa Rabbi Akiva? Is the
רישא reisha רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and the סיפא seifa רבי עקיבא?
Rabbi Akiva? לא כולה רבי עקיבא היא. Lo kula Rabbi Akiva hi.
It's all רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. והכא במאי עסקינן כשפיטמו. Vehacha bemai
askinan keshepitmu. Here the point is like this. It's all רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. So when it goes down, you understand why now you
get less, okay, because you had a percentage of it. Why when
it goes up don't you? you equally get more? So it says
because when it went up, it didn't just go up by it
didn't just get up by went up by itself. The original owner
actually fattened the animal. The increase in value is based on the
effort and the contribution and the investment of the original owner. And
therefore you're not going to get reap those benefits. Now, תוספות Tosafot
says that actually not so clear. Let's say we are partners in
a field. Charlie and I are partners in a field. And me
without telling Charlie I go and I plow it, and I put
in the fertilizer and I do all these things to make it
worth more. Now, Charlie might have to pay me for my effort,
for my investment, you know, for all those things, but it's still
his field, he still reaps some of the benefit, you know, the
increased value. I don't keep all of the increased value. I did
it on his field, right? So even if he has to like
reimburse me and pay me and all those things, he still benefits.
So תוספות Tosafot is bothered with that, and תוספות Tosafot has whatever
answer תוספות Tosafot has. But the basic point of the גמרא Gemara
is you don't get all of the benefit in this case cause
a lot of that was done because of the investment of the
מזיק. mazik. So maybe you reap some of the benefit because you're
a part owner according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but you don't
reap all of the benefit because it was done by the contributions
of the מזיק. mazik. Okay, so that כשהפטימו. keshe-pitmu. So the גמרא
Gemara says אימא רישא. eima reisha. Let's look at the beginning. שבח
ועמד על ארבע מאות זוז נותן לו כשעת הנזק. Shavach ve-amad al
arba me'ot zuz notein lo k'sha'at ha-nezak. Here it says when it
got worth more, you pay like the original amount, right? That's this
case. אי כשהפטימו צריכא למימר? Ee keshe-pitmu tzricha le-meimar?
So if you're talking about here that the owner of this one
is the one that fattened it, made it worth more, of course
he can't go ahead and, you know, ask for,
well then it's obvious, which way is it obvious? It's obvious that...
well, it's obvious, oh no, because רש"י Rashi says there's two חידושים
chiddushim here about the idea of when it went up value. One
חידוש chiddush is that the מזיק mazik doesn't pay him for the
loss from 800. But the other חידוש chiddush is that the מזיק
mazik pays him at all. Maybe the מזיק mazik can say, hey
buddy,
your cow's worth 400 more than it was originally worth. I don't
owe you anything. Okay, that would be a counter argument, another argument.
I shouldn't have to pay you at all. It's not worth less
than it was originally worth. And the answer is no, no, no,
it still is worth less, you do have to pay me because
if it weren't for your damage it would be worth even more,
it would be worth 800. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is saying
that that idea, the הוה אמינא havah amina that I could claim
I don't have to pay you because it's worth more, that would
be a crazy הוה אמינא havah amina if the only reason it's
worth more is because this guy actually fattened it and made it
worth more. So of course in that case you can't say, oh,
I shouldn't pay you, it's worth more. It's only worth more because
I invested in it. Okay. אי כשהפטימו Ee keshe-pitmu so
אי כשהפטימו צריכא למימר? Ee keshe-pitmu tzricha le-meimar? אמר רב פפא רישא
משכחת לה בין דפטמה פטומי בין דשבחא ממילא. Amar Rav Pappa reisha
mishkachat lah bein de-pitmah pitumei bein de-shavchah mi-meila. Okay, in the first
case when it went up to 400 and it could have gone
up to 800, that's however it went up to 400, whether it
was fattened or whether it just naturally got worth more. ואיצטריך לאשמועינן
דהיכא דשבחא ממילא נותן לו כשעת הנזק. ve-itztarich le-ashmi'inan de-heicha de-shavchah mi-meila
notein lo k'sha'at ha-nezak.
So even if it naturally went up to 400, I don't have
the right to say, hey buddy, why should I pay you anything,
it's worth more than it originally worth. No, you still have to
pay me because if it weren't for you, it would be worth
800 and not 400. So in the first case, it got better
whether it was fattened or whether it got better by itself. סיפא
לא משכחת לה אלא כשהפטימו. seifa lo mishkachat lah ela keshe-pitmu.
In this case though, the reason when it went up, the only
reason you don't gain in the increased value was because it was
fattened by the original owner. And in that case, the original owner
reaps most of the increased value, not you. Alright, that was a
little bit confusing, but the basic point is that it's according to
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So now the גמרא Gemara says כחש כשעת
העמדה בדין. kichesh k'sha'at ha-amadah ba-din. Now, back to this idea when
it goes down, you have to pay, you pay based on this
amount and not based on this amount. So the גמרא Gemara says
כחש מחמת מאי, kichesh machmat mai, why did it go down?
אילימא דכחשה מחמת מלאכה, Ee-eima dikicheshah machmat melacha, because here שמעון Shimon
had been working it and that's why it went down, he had
been like, you know, he had been mistreating it or whatever, you
know, it was due to שמעון's Shimon actions. So in that case,
לימא ליה עד דמכחשת ואנת יהבת? leima leh ad mikichshat va-anat ya-havat?
So of course, why should I pay for now that it's worth
100? The reason it's worth 100 now is because you were working
it and you got it to be and you made it go
down in value. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב אשי דכחש
מחמת מכה. Amar Rav Ashi dikichesh machmat makah. No, no, no, in
this case where you pay based on the 100, it's not that
it's just the market changed and it's not that it was being
worked by the original owner. It went down to 100 because of
the original injury. And in that case, דאמר ליה קרנא דתורך קבירא
בה. d'amar leh kurna de-torecha k'vira beh. I, שמעון, Shimon, says to
ראובן, Reuven, the reason it's worth 100 even though that was a
few days later, it's as if the horn of your ox is
still in my ox's body, meaning That depreciation is ultimately based on
the original injury. So that's not seen as גרמא. grama. That's seen
as how do you assess the original injury? You don't say the
original injury was 50 and everything happened afterwards was גרמא. grama. Everything
that happened afterwards was part of the original, was resulting from the
original injury, and that's how you assess the original injury. Okay, so
this was again, we've had a couple גמרות Gemaras where it's gotten
a little complicated, but the basic point here is, is if this
goes up in value, I don't pay for the loss of increase,
I only pay for the value. If it goes down though, because
that's just loss of profit. If it goes down as a result
of the original injury, then that's how you assess the actual cost
of the original injury. In this case, when it changes, according to
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you really should lose if it gets worth
less and gain if it gets worth more. But if the original
owner was the one who fattened it, and it was all due
to the efforts of the original owner, then the original owner is
the one who reaps most of the increase. All right, so that
was some נפקא מינות nafka minas of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael about being a part owner or having a
lien on it where again, the גמרא Gemara said according to רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, according to the ברייתא, braita, it sounds like according
to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the lien is not so strong. But
what the גמרא Gemara did is it made the lien pretty strong
according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, so even if the original owner
sold it, the נזק nezek can go and retrieve it etc., but
nevertheless there are the נפקא מינות nafka minas that we mentioned. Okay,
now we get to the actual parsing of the case in the
תורה. Torah. Let's take a look.
שור ששוה מאתים שנגח שור ששוה מאתים ואין הנבילה יפה כלום. Shor
sheshaveh matayim shenagach shor sheshaveh matayim ve'ein haneveilah yafah klum. So you
have an ox worth 200 that gored an ox worth 200, and
the נבילה neveilah is worth nothing. Okay, אמר רבי מאיר, amar Rabbi
Meir, על זה נאמר, al zeh ne'emar, this is the case in
the תורה, Torah, ומכרו את השור החי וחצו את כספו. umachru et
hashor hachai vechatzu et kaspo. You split the live cow, okay, so
it's a simple case of
200 and 200 goes down to zero. So the debt is 100.
So since the debt is 100, that's the case of ומכרו את
השור החי וחצו את כספו. umachru et hashor hachai vechatzu et kaspo.
Okay, that's the case in the תורה, Torah, they now become part
owners in that cattle. Okay, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
אמר ליה רבי יהודה וכן הלכה. Amar lei Rabbi Yehuda vechen halacha.
You know what? You're right, that is the הלכה, halacha, but that
doesn't, that's not what the תורה Torah is talking about. קיימת ומכרו
את השור החי וחצו את כספו ולא קיימת וגם את המת יחצון.
Kiyyamta umachru et hashor hachai vechatzu et kaspo velo kiyyamta vegam et
hamet yechetzun. But if it's worth zero, why is the תורה Torah
telling you split the dead body? Why do you have, here's the
dead cow. Okay, looks like a person, I don't care, okay. Why
do you have to split, I don't know, anyway. Why do you
have to split the cow? The cow is worth zero.
Okay, so ואיזה, ve'eizeh, so what is the case in the תורה?
Torah? זה שור ששוה מאתים שנגח שור ששוה מאתים והנבילה יפה חמישים.
Zeh shor sheshaveh matayim shenagach shor sheshaveh matayim vehaneveilah yafah chamishim. No,
no, no, it's worth 50. Okay. And in that case, שזה נוטל
חצי חי וחצי מת וזה נוטל חצי חי וחצי מת. shezeh notel
chatzi chai vechatzi met vezeh notel chatzi chai vechatzi met. In that
case, so they split it, so it's 100 and 100,
and here they split that, and that's the מת, met, and that's
25 and 25. So each one walks away with 125, okay. So
that's the חי, chai, this is the חי chai and that's the
מת, met, each one gets 125. Now, if each one gets 125,
how much did each person lose? Because each person started with a
200 dollar cow. So how much did each person lose? 75. How
much was the damage? 150, right? 150 was the damage, so חצי
נזק, chatzi nezek, everybody lost 75, okay. So now, presumably nobody disagrees
with that, right? Everybody agrees that it's half damages, so why does,
what's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda whether the תורה Torah is talking
about is that it's worth zero or the תורה Torah is talking
about that it's worth 50? Let's take a look.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. שור ששוה מאתים שנגח שור ששוה מאתים והנבילה
יפה חמישים זוז, Shor sheshaveh matayim shenagach shor sheshaveh matayim vehaneveilah yafah
chamishim zuz, שזה נוטל חצי חי וחצי מת וזה נוטל חצי חי
וחצי מת, shezeh notel chatzi chai vechatzi met vezeh notel chatzi chai
vechatzi met, וזהו שאמר בתורה דברי רבי יהודה. vezehu she'amar batorah divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that's the case,
that actually the נבילה neveilah is worth something and it still works
out to half damages. Okay.
רבי מאיר אומר אין זה שור האמור בתורה. Rabbi Meir omer ein
zeh shor ha'amur batorah. That's not the case in the תורה. Torah.
אלא שור ששוה מאתים שנגח שור ששוה מאתים ואין הנבילה יפה כלום.
Ela shor sheshaveh matayim shenagach shor sheshaveh matayim ve'ein haneveilah yafah klum.
When the carcass is worth nothing. על זה נאמר ומכרו את השור
החי וחצו את כספו. Al zeh ne'emar machru et hashor hachai vechatzu
et kaspo. אלא מה אני מקיים וגם את המת יחצון? Ela mah
ani mikayyem vegam et hamet yechetzun? So according to him, if the
נבילה neveilah is zero, what does it mean split the נבילה? neveilah?
So it says it doesn't mean split the נבילה, neveilah, what it
means is פחת שפחתו מיתה מחצין בחי. pchat shepichaso mitah machatzin bechai.
That's telling you the principle. וגם את המת יחצון vegam et hamet
yechetzun does not mean split the carcass. It means the amount that
it depreciated because it is dead, you split the loss. וגם את
המת יחצון vegam et hamet yechetzun means split the loss, split the
amount that it depreciated due to the death. But it does not
mean split the carcass. Now, what are you really debating? Because everybody
would agree in this case you pay 75. So what is רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*'s telling you by emphasizing split the carcass
and what is רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* resisting? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, so מכדי *michdi* let's take
a look says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. בין רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
בין רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda האי מאה ועשרין וחמישה שקיל והאי מאה
ועשרין וחמישה שקיל *Bein Rabbi Meir bein Rabbi Yehuda hai mea ve'esrin
vechamisha shakil vehai mea ve'esrin vechamisha shakil*. In the case of going
down of of the carcass being worth fifty, everyone walks away with
125, you pay 75. מאי בינייהו *mai beinaihu*, what are they really
debating? So אמר רבא פחת נבילה pchas neveilah איכא בינייהו *amar Rava
pchat neveila ika beinaihu*. Ah, you remember the פחת נבילה pchas neveilah
*pchat neveila*. Who has to deal with the carcass and who suffers
the depreciation of the carcass? רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir סבר פחת נבילה
neveilah דניזק הוי *Rabbi Meir savar pchat neveila de'nizak havei*. רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says I do not want to say split
the carcass. Like you got to just admit that רבי Rebbi, מאיר
*Rabbi Meir*'s less פשט pshat *pshat* of the תורה Torah *Torah*. גם
יחצון *gam yetachatzun* sounds like you're saying split the carcass. So why
is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* resisting it? Because רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
is saying the carcass, that's all the original owner's, that's all the
ניזק nizak's *nizak*'s. I pay for the depreciation when it died, but
you, the original owner of the dead cow, you have to take
the carcass away. That's not my responsibility at this point. Okay, I
just pay for the difference between for being alive and being dead.
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says split the carcass makes me
a part owner in your carcass and means that if it continues
to depreciate, I will I will suffer that loss. Okay, so רבי
מאיר סבר פחת נבילה neveilah דניזק הוי *Rabbi Meir savar pchat neveila
de'nizak havei*. The ניזק nizak *nizak* deals with the carcass, we do
not split the carcass, it's all the ניזק nizak *nizak*. רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda סבר לא פחת נבילה neveilah דמזיק הוי פלגא *Rabbi Yehuda
savar no pchat neveila de'mazik havei palga*. That the מזיק mazik *mazik*
splits half of the depreciation of the carcass. Yes, you have to
split the carcass as well, and if it depreciates, the מזיק mazik
*mazik* will take some of that loss. Okay, אמר ליה אביי אם
כן *amar lei Abaye im ken*, if that's true, מצינו לרבי יהודה
תם Tam חמור ממועד *matzinu l'Rabbi Yehuda tam chamur mi'muad*.
That the תם Tam *tam* is more strict than a מועד Mu'ad.
*muad* because you remember the normal rule is by the בור *bor*,
by a מועד Mu'ad *muad*, by every other animal, by every other
case, the ניזק nizak *nizak* gets the carcass and I just pay
for the loss. So here all of a sudden תם Tam. *tam*,
which is the most the most lenient of payments in the תורה
*Torah*, right? I now have to be a part owner of that
dead carcass and suffer the loss? So וכי תימא הכא נמי *vechi
teima hacha nami*. Yeah, maybe, maybe that's just arbitrary an arbitrary point
that you pay more in a case of a תם Tam, *tam*.
Maybe we got you off so easy in general, maybe you'll have
to deal with the carcass. No, כדתנן *kedetnan*, because actually next no
actually we see that there are ways in which רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says we're going to be more strict by a
תם Tam *tam*. We taught in the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*, רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda אומר תם Tam חייב ומועד פטור *Rabbi Yehuda omer tam
chayav ve'muad patur*. That actually if you do a minimum amount of
שמירה *shemira*, you're חייב *chayav* in a case of תם *tam* and
you're פטור *patur* in a case of מועד Mu'ad. *muad*. This is
quite ironic, we're going to see it later, but he actually says
you need to do less שמירה *shemira* to be exempt for a
מועד Mu'ad, *muad* than to be exempt for a תם *tam*. Okay,
so maybe רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says yes, maybe we
are stricter by a תם *tam* and maybe you do have to
suffer the loss of the carcass. גמרא *Gemara* says no, אימא דשמעת
ליה לרבי יהודה *eima deshamat lei lRabbi Yehuda*, when does רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* say we're stricter by a case of a תם *tam*,
meaning שמירה *shemira*, דכתיבי קרא *deksivei kra*, when it comes to guarding
the animal, because there there are פסוקים pesukim *psukim* it's based on.
אבל לענין תשלומין מי שמעת ליה *aval le'inyan tashlumin mi'shamat lei*, when
did you ever hear that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says that when
it comes to paying we're going to be more strict by a
תם *tam*? Paying a תם *tam* is always more lenient. Okay, והתניא
*veha tanya*, and I'll show you that. We taught in a ברייתא
*Baraita*, רבי יהודה אומר יכול שור שווה מנה שנגח שור שווה חמש
סלעים והנבילה יפה סלע *Rabbi Yehuda omer yachol shor shaveh mane she'nagach
shor shaveh chamesh s'la'im ve'haneveila yafa sela*. Now a סלע *sela* is
worth four זוז *zuz*. Okay, so you have
a hundred animal
goring something worth twenty. I'm going to just convert it all to
זוז *zuz*. Okay, 100 goring 20, okay, so והנבילה יפה סלע *ve'haneveila
yafa sela*, and then now this is worth four, okay, the סלע
*sela*. זה נוטל חצי חיה וחצי מתה *zeh notel chatzi chaya ve'chatzi
meisa*. Now what would happen if you would follow the פשט pshat.
*pshat* of the תורה *Torah*? Okay, what would happen if פשט pshat
*pshat* of פשט *pshat* of the תורה *Torah*? You split this 50-50,
okay, you split this, okay, two and two, okay, each one walks
away with 52, right? Okay, so now you, how much did you
the ניזק nizak's *nizak* lose out?
Eighteen. How much you walk away with? 52. Pretty good deal for
you the ניזק *nizak*, right? If you always split the מזיק mazik
*mazik* rather than looking at the actual loss, right, then if the
מזיק mazik *mazik* is worth a lot more than the ניזק *nizak*,
you come away with a lot of money. Okay, so זה נוטל
חצי חיה וחצי מתה זה נוטל חצי חיה וחצי מתה אמרת וכי
מועד Mu'ad. למאי יצא *zeh notel chatzi chaya ve'chatzi meisa, zeh notel
chatzi chaya ve'chatzi meisa amarta vechi muad l'mai yatza*? Why was the
מועד *muad* made different than the תם *tam*? להחמיר עליו או להקל
עליו *le'hachmir alav o le'hakel alav*? To be strict by the מועד
*muad* or to be lenient? הוי אומר להחמיר עליו *hevei omer le'hachmir
alav*. Obviously the מועד *muad* pays more. ומה מועד אינו משלם אלא
מה שהזיק *uma muad eino meshalem ela mah she'hizik*, a מועד *muad*
only going to pay the amount of the damage, תם הקל כל
שכן *tam ha'kal kol she'ken* assumed תם הקל *tam ha'kal*. So anyway
that's what רבי יהודה is saying, you can't read the פסוקים pesukim
always apply it. You can apply it if the animals are worth
the same. You can't apply it if the animals are worth different
amounts. But what our purpose of it is saying is, you see
that רבי יהודה rejects the possibility that a תם would ever be
more strict than a מועד. So how could רבי יהודה say that
you suffer the פחת נבילה neveilah of a תם if by a
מועד the פחת נבילה is always the ניזק's responsibility? So the גמרא
says אלא אמר רבי יוחנן ela amar Rebbi Yochanan fine, שבח נבילה
איכא בינייהו. shevach neveilah ika beiniyahu. When the נבילה depreciated, the ניזק
suffers it because that's going to be like a מועד. Okay if
the ניזק suffers it in a מועד, the ניזק is going to
suffer in the תם. But let's say the נבילה actually increases in
value. That's where רבי יהודה is going to say because it's a
תם, you're a part owner in the נבילה and you will gain
any increase in value of the נבילה in order to make your
payment more lenient. דמר סבר דניזק הוי ומר סבר פלגא. demar savar
denizak havei umar savar palga. No, you actually, the מזיק mazik actually
gets half of the increase in value.
Okay והיינו דקקשיא ליה לרבי יהודה vehaynu dekakashya lei l'Rebbi Yehuda and
that's why רבי יהודה was raising this point. He says השתא דאמרת
תחוס רחמנא עילויה דמזיק דשחלי שבחא, hashta de'amart tachos rachmana iluyei demazik
deshachli shevacha, if the תורה is going lenient on the מזיק in
a case of תם and is actually saying that in the case
of תם that you actually can even, you know, your payments can
get ameliorated by the increase in the value of the קרקע, karka,
that you actually are part owner in the קרקע karka not to
suffer loss, but to actually, you know, gain from it if it
goes up in value, יכול שור שוה חמש סלעים שנגח שור שוה
מנה והנבלה יפה, yachol shor shaveh chamesh sela'im shenagach shor shaveh maneh
vehaneveilah yafah, you know what actually this is a new case and
it's already 8:30 so we're going to have to end here. Okay
unfortunately. Okay but the bottom line is, is that we is that
for רבי, this question of splitting the קרקע, karka, okay,
רבי מאיר resists it because רבי מאיר says what we normally say,
the קרקע karka is the ניזק's responsibility, end of the story. רבי
יהודה wants to read פשט of the פסוקים that they do split
the קרקע, karka, at least when the animals are worth equivalent amounts,
they split the קרקע. karka. Okay but the גמרא says you cannot
read that completely like פשט. Completely like פשט would mean that the
מזיק would suffer in the depreciation of the קרקע. karka. That's not
true even in a case of מועד. So we're going to say
fine, the מזיק won't suffer in the depreciation of the קרקע, karka,
but he's a part owner in the קרקע karka so that he
will, he will benefit from the increased value of the קרקע. karka.
Okay? So the basic debate of רבי יהודה and רבי מאיר in
the משנה, do you split the קרקע, karka, is a debate of
will the מזיק benefit from the increased value of the קרקע? karka?
That רבי יהודה will say yes and רבי מאיר will say no.
Alright, we'll continue.